<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby | Bear Metal]]></title>
  <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-12T13:39:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://bearmetal.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bear Metal OÜ]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Help! My Rails App Is Melting Under the Launch Day Load]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/help-my-rails-app-is-melting-under-the-launch-day-load/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T13:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/help-my-rails-app-is-melting-under-the-launch-day-load</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><figure markdown="1">
  <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pasukaru76/4484360302">
    <img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4065/4484360302_70ac4b6a8d_o_d.jpg">
  </a></p>

<p>  <figcaption>
    <p>
      Photo by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pasukaru76/4484360302">Pascal</a>
    </p>
  </figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>It was to be our day. The Finnish championship relay in orienteering was about to be held close to us, in a terrain type we knew inside and out. We had a great team, with both young guns and old champions. My friend Samuli had been fourth in the individual middle distance championships the day before. My only job was to handle the first leg securely and pass the baton to the more experienced and tougher guys who would then take care of our success. And I failed miserably.</p>

<p>My legs were like dough from the beginning. I was supposed to be in good shape, but I couldn&rsquo;t keep up with anyone. I was supposed to take it easy and orienteer cleanly, but I ran like a headless chicken, making a mistake after another. Although I wouldn&rsquo;t learn the term until years later, this was my crash course to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ego_depletion">ego depletion</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>The day before the relay we organized the middle distance Finnish champs in my old hometown Parainen. For obvious reasons, I was the de facto webmaster of our club pages, which also hosted the result service. The site was running on OpenACS, a system running on TCL I had a year or so of work experience with. I was supposed to know it.</p>

<p>After the race was over, I headed back to my friend&rsquo;s place, opened up my laptop… only to find out that the local orienteering forums were ablaze with complaints about our results page being down. Crap.</p>

<p>After hours or hunting down the issue, getting help on the OpenACS IRC channel, serving the results from a static page meanwhile, I finally managed to fix the issue. The app wasn&rsquo;t running enough server processes to keep up with the load. And the most embarrassing thing was that <em>the load wasn&rsquo;t even that high</em> – from high dozens to hundreds of simultaneous users. I headed to bed with my head spinning, hoping to scramble up my self confidence for the next day&rsquo;s race (with well-known results).</p>

<p>What does this have to do with Ruby or Rails? Nothing, really. And yet everything. The point is that most of us have a similar story to share. It&rsquo;s much more common to have a meltdown story with a reasonably low number of users than actually have a slashdotting/hackernewsing/daring fireball hit your app. If you aren&rsquo;t old enough to have gone through something like this, you probably will. But you don&rsquo;t have to.</p>

<hr />

<p>During the dozen or so years since the aforementioned episode, I&rsquo;ve gone through some serious loads. Some of them we have handled badly, but most – including the <a href="http://wildfireapp.blogspot.fi/2009/04/wildfire-runs-facebook-site-governance.html">Facebook terms of service vote campaign</a> – with at least reasonable grace. This series of articles about Rails performance builds upon those war stories.</p>

<p>We have already posted a couple of articles to start off the series.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="/theden/rails-garbage-collection-naive-defaults/">Rails Garbage Collection: Naive Defaults</a></li>
<li><a href="/theden/does-rails-scale/">Does Rails Scale?</a></li>
<li><a href="/theden/rails-garbage-collection-age-matters/">Rails Garbage Collection: Age Matters</a></li>
</ol>


<p>This article will serve as kind of a belated intro to the series, introducing our high level principles regarding the subject but without going more to the details.</p>

<h2>The Bear Metal ironclad rules of Rails performance</h2>

<h3>Scalability is not the same as performance</h3>

<p>As I already noted in <a href="/theden/does-rails-scale/">Does Rails Scale?</a>, it&rsquo;s worth pointing out that performance is not the same thing as scalability. They are related for sure. But you can perform similarly poorly from your first to your millionth user and be “scalable”. There is also the difference that performance is right here and now. If your app scales well, you can just throw more hardware (virtual or real) at the problem and solve it by that.</p>

<p>The good news is that Rails scales quite well out of the box for the vast majority of real-world needs. You probably won&rsquo;t be the next Twitter or even Basecamp. In your dreams and VC prospectus maybe, but let&rsquo;s be honest, the odds are stacked against you. So don&rsquo;t sweat about that too much.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, you do want your app to perform well enough for your initial wave of users.</p>

<h3>Perceived performance is what matters</h3>

<p>There are basically three different layers of performance for any web app: the server level (I&rsquo;m bundling everything from the data store to the frontend server here), browser rendering and the performance perceived by the user. The two latter ones are very close to each other but not exactly the same. You can tweak the perceived performance with tricks on the UI level, something that often isn&rsquo;t even considered performance.</p>

<p>The most important lesson here is that the perceived performance is what matters. It makes no difference what your synthetic performance tests on your server say if the UI of the app feels sluggish. There is no panacea to solve this, but make no mistake, it is what matters when the chicken come home to roost.</p>

<h3>Start with quick, large, and obvious wins</h3>

<p>The fact is that even a modest amount of users can make your app painfully slow. The good thing is that you can probably fix that just with hitting the low-hanging fruit. You won&rsquo;t believe how many Rails apps reveal that they&rsquo;re running in the development mode even in production by – when an error occurs – leaking the whole error trace out to the end user.</p>

<p>Other examples of issues that are fairly easy to spot and fix are N+1 query issues with ActiveRecord associations, missing database indeces, and running a single, non-concurrent app server instance, where any longer-running action will block the whole app from other users.</p>

<h3>YAGNI</h3>

<p>Once you have squashed all the low-hanging fruit with your metal-reinforced bat, relax. Tuning app performance shouldn&rsquo;t be your top priority at the moment – unless it is, but in that case you will know for sure. What you should be focusing on is how to get paying customers and how you can make them kick ass. If you have clear performance issues, by all means fix them. However…</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t assume, measure</h3>

<p>You probably don&rsquo;t have any idea how many users your app needs to support from the get go. That&rsquo;s fine. The reality will teach you. As long as you don&rsquo;t royally fuck up the share nothing (and 12 factor if you&rsquo;re on a cloud platform such as Heroku) architecture, you should be able to react to issues quickly.</p>

<p>That said, you probably do want to do some baseline load testing with your app if you&rsquo;re opening for a much larger private group or the public. The good news is that it is very cheap to spin up a virtual server instance just for a couple of hours and hit your app hard with it. Heck, you can handle the baseline from your laptop if needed. With that you should be able to get over the initial, frightening launch.</p>

<p>Once your app is up and running under load from real users, your tuning work starts for real. Only now will you be able to measure where the real hot paths and bottlenecks in your app are, based on real usage data, not just assumptions. At this point you&rsquo;ll have a plethora of tools at your disposal, from the good old <a href="https://github.com/wvanbergen/request-log-analyzer">request log analyzer</a> to commercial offerings such as <a href="https://www.skylight.io">Skylight</a>, and <a href="http://newrelic.com">New Relic</a>.</p>

<p>On the frontend most browsers have nowadays developer tools to optimize end-user performance, from Chrome and Safari&rsquo;s built-in developer tools to <a href="http://getfirebug.com">Firebug</a> for Firefox.</p>

<h2>Wrap-up</h2>

<p>In this introductory article to building performant Rails (or any, for that matter) web apps, we took a look at five basic rules of performance optimization:</p>

<ol>
<li>Scalability is not the same as performance.</li>
<li>Perceived performance is what matters.</li>
<li>Start with the low-hanging fruit.</li>
<li>YAGNI</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t assume, measure.</li>
</ol>


<p>We will get (much) more in the details of Rails performance optimization in later articles. At that point we&rsquo;ll enter a territory where one size does not fit all anymore. However, whatever your particular performance problem is, you should keep the five rules above at the top your mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Install Ruby 2.2.0 on OS X Yosemite With Homebrew and Rbenv]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/install-ruby-2-dot-2-0-yosemite-openssl-error/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-06T16:15:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/install-ruby-2-dot-2-0-yosemite-openssl-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When trying to install Ruby 2.2.0 on Yosemite with <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">rbenv</a> and <a href="http://brew.sh">Homebrew</a>, I got a weird error:</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~ ✗ rbenv install 2.2.0
Downloading ruby-2.2.0.tar.gz...
-&gt; http://dqw8nmjcqpjn7.cloudfront.net/7671e394abfb5d262fbcd3b27a71bf78737c7e9347fa21c39e58b0bb9c4840fc
Installing ruby-2.2.0...

BUILD FAILED (OS X 10.10.1 using ruby-build 20141225)

Inspect or clean up the working tree at /var/folders/s_/_zh3skrd0qz2933nns5y425r0000gn/T/ruby-build.20150106151200.81466
Results logged to /var/folders/s_/_zh3skrd0qz2933nns5y425r0000gn/T/ruby-build.20150106151200.81466.log

Last 10 log lines:
make[2]: *** Waiting for unfinished jobs....
compiling raddrinfo.c
compiling ifaddr.c
make[1]: *** [ext/openssl/all] Error 2
make[1]: *** Waiting for unfinished jobs....
linking shared-object zlib.bundle
linking shared-object socket.bundle
linking shared-object date_core.bundle
linking shared-object ripper.bundle
make: *** [build-ext] Error 2
</code></pre>

<p>When I opened up the log file mentioned in the output above, I could see the actual cause of the error:</p>

<pre><code>ossl_ssl.c:125:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_2_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_2),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_2_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:126:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_2_server_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_2_server),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_2_server_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:127:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_2_client_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_2_client),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_2_client_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:131:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_1_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_1),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_1_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:132:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_1_server_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_1_server),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_1_server_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:133:5: error: use of undeclared identifier 'TLSv1_1_client_method'
    OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(TLSv1_1_client),
    ^
ossl_ssl.c:119:69: note: expanded from macro 'OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY'
#define OSSL_SSL_METHOD_ENTRY(name) { #name, (SSL_METHOD *(*)(void))name##_method }
                                                                    ^
&lt;scratch space&gt;:148:1: note: expanded from here
TLSv1_1_client_method
^
ossl_ssl.c:210:21: error: invalid application of 'sizeof' to an incomplete type 'const struct &lt;anonymous struct at ossl_ssl.c:115:14&gt; []'
    for (i = 0; i &lt; numberof(ossl_ssl_method_tab); i++) {
                    ^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:19:35: note: expanded from macro 'numberof'
#define numberof(ary) (int)(sizeof(ary)/sizeof((ary)[0]))
                                  ^~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:1127:13: warning: using the result of an assignment as a condition without parentheses [-Wparentheses]
            if (rc = SSL_shutdown(ssl))
                ~~~^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:1127:13: note: place parentheses around the assignment to silence this warning
            if (rc = SSL_shutdown(ssl))
                   ^
                (                     )
ossl_ssl.c:1127:13: note: use '==' to turn this assignment into an equality comparison
            if (rc = SSL_shutdown(ssl))
                   ^
                   ==
ossl_ssl.c:2194:23: error: invalid application of 'sizeof' to an incomplete type 'const struct &lt;anonymous struct at ossl_ssl.c:115:14&gt; []'
    ary = rb_ary_new2(numberof(ossl_ssl_method_tab));
                      ^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:19:35: note: expanded from macro 'numberof'
#define numberof(ary) (int)(sizeof(ary)/sizeof((ary)[0]))
                                  ^~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:2195:21: error: invalid application of 'sizeof' to an incomplete type 'const struct &lt;anonymous struct at ossl_ssl.c:115:14&gt; []'
    for (i = 0; i &lt; numberof(ossl_ssl_method_tab); i++) {
                    ^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
ossl_ssl.c:19:35: note: expanded from macro 'numberof'
#define numberof(ary) (int)(sizeof(ary)/sizeof((ary)[0]))
                                  ^~~~~
1 warning and 9 errors generated.
make[2]: *** [ossl_ssl.o] Error 1
make[2]: *** Waiting for unfinished jobs....
compiling raddrinfo.c
compiling ifaddr.c
make[1]: *** [ext/openssl/all] Error 2
make[1]: *** Waiting for unfinished jobs....
linking shared-object zlib.bundle
linking shared-object socket.bundle
linking shared-object date_core.bundle
linking shared-object ripper.bundle
make: *** [build-ext] Error 2
</code></pre>

<p>The weird thing here is that I did not get the usual &lsquo;Missing the OpenSSL lib?&rsquo; warning. The lib <em>was</em> found but somehow the headers were fucked up. It also did not happen with older rbenv Rubies.</p>

<p>Thanks to <a href="https://bearmetal.eu/team/tarmo/">Tarmo</a> I found the solution <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/THRIFT-2515?focusedCommentId=14012758&amp;page=com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.issuetabpanels:comment-tabpanel#comment-14012758">here</a>.</p>

<p>What I had to do was this:</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~  brew update
➜  ~  brew install openssl
➜  ~  /usr/local/opt/openssl/bin/c_rehash
</code></pre>

<p>Now make sure that your new binary is in your PATH before the system one.</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~  ln -s /usr/local/opt/openssl/bin/openssl /usr/local/bin/openssl
➜  ~ which openssl
/usr/bin/openssl
➜  ~ echo $PATH
/usr/local/heroku/bin:/Users/jarkko/.rbenv/shims:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin:/usr/local/bin
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s no good. Let&rsquo;s fix our PATH. I&rsquo;m using zsh, so for me it&rsquo;s set in <code>~/.zshrc</code>. Your particular file depends on the shell you&rsquo;re using (for bash it would be <code>~/.bashrc</code> or <code>~/.bash_profile</code>, but see the caveat <a href="http://www.joshstaiger.org/archives/2005/07/bash_profile_vs.html">here</a>).</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~ vim ~/.zshrc
# Change the line that sets PATH so that /usr/local/bin
# comes BEFORE /usr/bin. For me, it looks like this:
# export PATH=/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin
</code></pre>

<p>Open up a new terminal window and check that the PATH is correct:</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~  echo $PATH
/usr/local/heroku/bin:/Users/jarkko/.rbenv/shims:/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/bin:/usr/sbin:/sbin
➜  ~  which openssl
/usr/local/bin/openssl
</code></pre>

<p>Better. Now, let&rsquo;s make sure that homebrew libs symlink to the newer openssl.</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~  brew unlink openssl
➜  ~  brew link --overwrite --force openssl
➜  ~  openssl version -a

OpenSSL 1.0.1j 15 Oct 2014
built on: Sun Dec  7 02:14:31 GMT 2014
platform: darwin64-x86_64-cc
options:  bn(64,64) rc4(ptr,char) des(idx,cisc,16,int) idea(int) blowfish(idx) 
compiler: clang -fPIC -fno-common -DOPENSSL_PIC -DZLIB_SHARED -DZLIB -DOPENSSL_THREADS -D_REENTRANT -DDSO_DLFCN -DHAVE_DLFCN_H -arch x86_64 -O3 -DL_ENDIAN -Wall -DOPENSSL_IA32_SSE2 -DOPENSSL_BN_ASM_MONT -DOPENSSL_BN_ASM_MONT5 -DOPENSSL_BN_ASM_GF2m -DSHA1_ASM -DSHA256_ASM -DSHA512_ASM -DMD5_ASM -DAES_ASM -DVPAES_ASM -DBSAES_ASM -DWHIRLPOOL_ASM -DGHASH_ASM
OPENSSLDIR: "/usr/local/etc/openssl"
</code></pre>

<p>Splendid.</p>

<p>After that, Ruby 2.2.0 installed cleanly without any specific parameters needed:</p>

<pre><code>➜  ~  rbenv install 2.2.0
Downloading ruby-2.2.0.tar.gz...
-&gt; http://dqw8nmjcqpjn7.cloudfront.net/7671e394abfb5d262fbcd3b27a71bf78737c7e9347fa21c39e58b0bb9c4840fc
Installing ruby-2.2.0...
Installed ruby-2.2.0 to /Users/jarkko/.rbenv/versions/2.2.0
</code></pre>

<p><strong>[UPDATE 1, Jan 7]</strong> The original version of this post told you to <code>rm /usr/bin/openssl</code>, based on the link above. As James Tucker pointed out, this is a horrible idea. I fixed the article so that we now fix the <code>$PATH</code> instead.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Garbage Collection: Age Matters]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/rails-garbage-collection-age-matters/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T20:26:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/rails-garbage-collection-age-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a <a href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/rails-garbage-collection-naive-defaults/">previous post</a> in the <a href="/theden/categories/rails-performance">Rails Performance</a> series we stated that the default garbage collection settings for <a href="http://www.rubyonrails.org">Ruby on Rails</a> applications are not optimal. In this post we&rsquo;ll explore the basics of object age in RGenGC, Ruby 2.1&rsquo;s new <em>restricted generational garbage collector</em>.</p>

<p>As a prerequisite of this and subsequent posts, basic understanding of a <em>mark and sweep</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> collector is assumed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/gc_mark_sweep.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>A somewhat simplified mark and sweep cycle goes like this:</p>

<ol>
<li>A mark and sweep collector traverses the object graph.</li>
<li>It checks which objects are in use (referenced) and which ones are not.</li>
<li>This is called object marking, aka. the <strong>MARK PHASE</strong>.</li>
<li>All unused objects are freed, making their memory available.</li>
<li>This is called sweeping, aka. the <strong>SWEEP PHASE</strong>.</li>
<li>Nothing changes for used objects.</li>
</ol>


<p>A GC cycle prior to Ruby 2.1 works like that. A typical Rails app boots with 300 000 live objects of which all need to be scanned during the <strong>MARK</strong> phase. That usually yields a smaller set to <strong>SWEEP</strong>.</p>

<p>A large percentage of the graph is going to be traversed over and over again but will never be reclaimed. This is not only CPU intensive during GC cycles, but also incurs memory overhead for accounting and anticipation for future growth.</p>

<h2>Old and young objects</h2>

<p><strong>What generally makes an object old?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><em>All new objects are considered to be young</em>.</li>
<li><em>Old objects survived at least one GC cycle (major or minor)</em> The collector thus reasons that the object will stick around and not become garbage quickly.</li>
</ul>


<p>The idea behind the new generational garbage collector is this:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>MOST OBJECTS DIE YOUNG.</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>To take advantage of this fact, the new GC classifies objects on the Ruby heap as either <strong>OLD</strong> or <strong>YOUNG</strong>. This segregation now allows the garbage collector to work with two distinct generations, with the <strong>OLD</strong> generation much less likely to yield much improvement towards recovering memory.</p>

<p>For a typical Rails request, some examples of old and new objects would be:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Old:</strong> compiled routes, templates, ActiveRecord connections, cached DB column info, classes, modules etc.</li>
<li><strong>New:</strong> short lived strings within a partial, a string column value from an ActiveRecord result, a coerced DateTime instance etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>Young objects are more likely to reference old objects than old objects referencing young objects. Old objects also frequently reference other old objects.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">  u = User.first
  #&lt;User id: 1, email: "lourens@something.com", encrypted_password: "blahblah...", reset_password_token: nil, reset_password_sent_at: nil, remember_created_at: nil, sign_in_count: 2, current_sign_in_at: "2014-10-31 11:52:30", last_sign_in_at: "2014-10-29 10:04:01", current_sign_in_ip: "127.0.0.1", last_sign_in_ip: "127.0.0.1", created_at: "2014-10-29 10:04:01", updated_at: "2014-11-30 14:07:15", provider: nil, uid: nil, first_name: "dfdsfds", last_name: "dfdsfds", confirmation_token: nil, confirmed_at: "2014-10-30 10:11:42", confirmation_sent_at: nil, unconfirmed_email: nil, onboarded_at: nil&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Notice how the transient attribute keys and names reference the long lived columns here:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">    {"id"=&gt;
       #&lt;ActiveRecord::ConnectionAdapters::PostgreSQLAdapter::OID::Integer:0x007fbe756d1d30&gt;,
      "email"=&gt;
       #&lt;ActiveRecord::ConnectionAdapters::PostgreSQLAdapter::OID::Identity:0x007fbe756d1718&gt;,
      "encrypted_password"=&gt;
       #&lt;ActiveRecord::ConnectionAdapters::PostgreSQLAdapter::OID::Identity:0x007fbe756d1718&gt;,
      "reset_password_token"=&gt;
       #&lt;ActiveRecord::ConnectionAdapters::PostgreSQLAdapter::OID::Identity:0x007fbe756d1718&gt;,
      "reset_password_sent_at"=&gt;
       #&lt;ActiveRecord::AttributeMethods::TimeZoneConversion::Type:0x007fbe741f63c0
        @column=
         #&lt;ActiveRecord::ConnectionAdapters::PostgreSQLAdapter::OID::Timestamp:0x007fbe756d0e58&gt;&gt;,
</code></pre>

<p>Age segregation is also just a classification &ndash; old and young objects aren&rsquo;t stored in distinct memory spaces &ndash; they&rsquo;re just conceptional buckets. The generation of an object refers to the amount of GC cycles it survived:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">irb(main):009:0&gt; ObjectSpace.dump([])
=&gt; "{\"address\":\"0x007fd24c007668\", \"type\":\"ARRAY\", \"class\":\"0x007fd24b872038\", \"length\":0, \"file\":\"(irb)\", \"line\":9, \"method\":\"irb_binding\", \"generation\":8, \"flags\":{\"wb_protected\":true}}\n"
irb(main):010:0&gt; GC.count
=&gt; 8
</code></pre>

<h2>What the heck is major and minor GC?</h2>

<p>You may have heard, read about or noticed in GC.stat output the terms &ldquo;minor&rdquo; and &ldquo;major&rdquo; GC.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">    irb(main):003:0&gt; pp GC.stat
    {:count=&gt;32,
     :heap_used=&gt;1181,
     :heap_length=&gt;1233,
     :heap_increment=&gt;50,
     :heap_live_slot=&gt;325148,
     :heap_free_slot=&gt;156231,
     :heap_final_slot=&gt;0,
     :heap_swept_slot=&gt;163121,
     :heap_eden_page_length=&gt;1171,
     :heap_tomb_page_length=&gt;10,
     :total_allocated_object=&gt;2050551,
     :total_freed_object=&gt;1725403,
     :malloc_increase=&gt;1462784,
     :malloc_limit=&gt;24750208,
     :minor_gc_count=&gt;26,
     :major_gc_count=&gt;6,
     :remembered_shady_object=&gt;3877,
     :remembered_shady_object_limit=&gt;4042,
     :old_object=&gt;304270,
     :old_object_limit=&gt;259974,
     :oldmalloc_increase=&gt;23639792,
     :oldmalloc_limit=&gt;24159190}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Minor GC (or &ldquo;partial marking&rdquo;):</strong> This cycle only traverses the young generation and is very fast. Based on the hypothesis that most objects die young, this GC cycle is thus the most effective at reclaiming back a large ratio of memory in proportion to objects traversed.</p>

<p>It runs quite often - 26 times for the GC dump of a booted Rails app above.</p>

<p><strong>Major GC:</strong> Triggered by out-of-memory conditions - Ruby heap space needs to be expanded (not OOM killer! :-)) Both old and young objects are traversed and it&rsquo;s thus significantly slower than a minor GC round. Generally when there&rsquo;s a significant increase in old objects, a major GC would be triggered. Every major GC cycle that an object survived bumps its current generation.</p>

<p>It runs much less frequently - six times for the stats dump above.</p>

<p>The following diagram represents a minor GC cycle (<strong>MARK</strong> phase completed, <strong>SWEEP</strong> still pending) that identifies and promotes some objects to old.</p>

<p><img src="/images/gc_first_minor.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>A subsequent minor GC cycle (<strong>MARK</strong> phase completed, <strong>SWEEP</strong> still pending) ignores old objects during the mark phase.</p>

<p><img src="/images/gc_second_minor.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Most of the reclaiming efforts are thus focussed on the young generation (new objects). Generally 95% of objects are dead by the first GC. The current generation of an object is the number of major GC cycles it has survived.</p>

<h2>RGenGC</h2>

<p>At a very high level C Ruby 2.1&rsquo;s collector has the following properties:</p>

<ul>
<li>High throughput - it can sustain a high rate of allocations / collections due to faster minor GC cycles and very rare major GC cycles.</li>
<li>GC pauses are still long (&ldquo;stop the world&rdquo;) for major GC cycles.</li>
<li>Generational collectors have much shorter mark cycles as they traverse only the young generation, most of the time.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is a marked improvement to the C Ruby GC and serves as a base for implementing other advanced features moving forward. Ruby 2.2 supports incremental GC and object ages beyond just old and new definitions. A major GC cycle in 2.1 still runs in a &ldquo;stop the world&rdquo; manner, whereas a more involved incremental implementation (Ruby 2.2) interleaves short steps of mark and sweep cycles between other VM operations.</p>

<h2>Object references</h2>

<p>In this simple example below we create a String array with three elements.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">    irb(main):001:0&gt; require 'objspace'
    =&gt; true
    irb(main):002:0&gt; ObjectSpace.trace_object_allocations_start
    =&gt; nil
    irb(main):003:0&gt; ary = %w(a b c)
    =&gt; ["a", "b", "c"]
</code></pre>

<p>Very much like a river flowing downstream, the array has knowledge of (a reference to) each of its String elements. On the contrary, the strings don&rsquo;t have an awareness of (or references back to) the array container.</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">    irb(main):004:0&gt; ObjectSpace.dump(ary)
    =&gt; "{\"address\":\"0x007fd24b890fd8\", \"type\":\"ARRAY\", \"class\":\"0x007fd24b872038\", \"length\":3, \"embedded\":true, \"references\":[\"0x007fd24b891050\", \"0x007fd24b891028\", \"0x007fd24b891000\"], \"file\":\"(irb)\", \"line\":3, \"method\":\"irb_binding\", \"generation\":7, \"flags\":{\"wb_protected\":true}}\n"
    irb(main):004:0&gt; ObjectSpace.reachable_objects_from(ary)
    =&gt; [Array, "a", "b", "c"]
    irb(main):006:0&gt; ObjectSpace.reachable_objects_from(ary[1])
    =&gt; [String]
    irb(main):007:0&gt; ObjectSpace.dump(ary[1])
    =&gt; "{\"address\":\"0x007fd24b891028\", \"type\":\"STRING\", \"class\":\"0x007fd24b829658\", \"embedded\":true, \"bytesize\":1, \"value\":\"b\", \"encoding\":\"UTF-8\", \"file\":\"(irb)\", \"line\":3, \"method\":\"irb_binding\", \"generation\":7, \"flags\":{\"wb_protected\":true, \"old\":true, \"marked\":true}}\n"
</code></pre>

<p>We stated earlier that:</p>

<p><strong>Young objects are more likely to reference old objects, than old objects referencing young objects. Old objects also frequently reference other old objects.</strong></p>

<p><em>However</em> it&rsquo;s possible for old objects to reference new objects. What happens when old objects reference new ones?</p>

<p>Old objects with references to new objects are stored in a &ldquo;remembered set&rdquo;. The remembered set is a container of references from old objects to new objects and is a shortcut for preventing heap scans for finding such references.</p>

<h2>Implications for Rails</h2>

<p>As our friend Ezra used to say, &ldquo;no code is faster than no code.&rdquo; The same applies to automatic memory management. Every object allocation also has a variable recycle cost. Allocation generally is low overhead as it happens once, except for the use case where there are no free object slots on the Ruby heap and a major GC is triggered as a result.</p>

<p>A major drawback of this limited segregation of OLD vs YOUNG is that <strong>many transient objects are in fact promoted to old during large contexts such as a Rails request</strong>. These long lived objects eventually become unexpected &ldquo;memory leaks&rdquo;. These transient objects can be conceptually classified as of &ldquo;medium lifetime&rdquo; as they need to stick around for the duration of a request. There&rsquo;s however a large probability that a minor GC would run during request lifetime, promoting young objects to old, effectively increasing their lifetime to well beyond the end of a request. This situation can only be revisited during a major GC which runs infrequently and sweeps both old and young objects.</p>

<p><strong>Each generation can be specifically tweaked, with the older generation being particularly important for balancing total process memory use with maintaining a minimal transient object set (young ones) per request. And subsequent too fast promotion from young to old generation.</strong></p>

<p><em>In our next post we will explore how you&rsquo;d approach tuning the Ruby GC for Rails applications, balancing tradeoffs of speed and memory. Leave your email address below and we&rsquo;ll let you know as soon as it&rsquo;s posted.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See the Ruby Hacking Guide&rsquo;s <a href="https://ruby-hacking-guide.github.io/gc.html">GC chapter</a> for further context and nitty gritty details. I&rsquo;d recommended scanning the content below the first few headings, until turned off by C.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Rails Scale?]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/does-rails-scale/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-19T15:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/does-rails-scale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><figure markdown="1">
  <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/soctech/43279549/">
    <img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/24/43279549_465d50976e_b_d.jpg">
  </a></p>

<p>  <figcaption>
    <p>
      Photo by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/soctech/43279549/">Soctech</a>
    </p>
  </figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>Back when Rails was still not mainstream, a common dismissal by developers using other – more established – technologies was that Rails is cool and stuff, but it will never scale<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. While the question isn&rsquo;t (compared to Rails&#8217; success) as common these days, it still appears in one form or another every once in a while.</p>

<p>Last week on the Ruby on Rails Facebook group, someone asked <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/rubyandrails/permalink/10153620823655752/">this question</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Can Rails stand up to making a social platform like FB with millions of users using it at the same time?</p>

<p>If so what are the pro&rsquo;s and the cons?</p></blockquote>

<p>So in other words, can Rails scale <em>a lot</em>?</p>

<p>Just as is customary for a Facebook group, the question got a lot of clueless answers. There were a couple of gems like this:</p>

<blockquote><p>Tony if you want to build some thing like FB, you need to learn deeper mountable engine and SOLID anti pattern.</p></blockquote>

<p>The worst however are answers from people who <em>don&rsquo;t know</em> they don&rsquo;t know shit but insist on giving advice that is only bound to either confuse the original poster or lead them astray – and probably both:</p>

<blockquote><p>Twitter is not a good example. They stopped using Rails because it couldn&rsquo;t handle millions of request per second. They began using Scala.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is of course mostly BS with a hint of truth in it, but we&rsquo;ll get back to that in a bit.</p>

<p>The issue with the question itself, is that <em>it&rsquo;s the wrong question to ask</em>, and this has nothing to do with Ruby or Rails per se.</p>

<p>Why is it the wrong question? Let&rsquo;s have a look.</p>

<p>Sure, Ruby is slow in raw performance. It has gotten a lot faster during the past decade, but it is still a highly dynamic interpreted scripting language. Its main shtick has always been programmer happiness, and its primary way to attain that goal has definitely not been to return from that test run as fast as possible. The same goes for Rails.</p>

<p>That said, there are two reasons bare Ruby performance doesn&rsquo;t matter <em>that</em> much. First, it&rsquo;s only a tiny part of the <strong>perceived app performance</strong> for the user. Rails has gone out of its way to automatically make the frontend of your web app performant. This includes frontend caching, asset pipeline, and more opinionated things like Turbolinks. You can of course screw all that up, but you would be amazed how much actual end-user performance you&rsquo;d miss if you&rsquo;d write the same app from scratch – not to mention the time you&rsquo;d waste building it.</p>

<p>Second, and most important for this discussion: <strong>scaling is not the same thing as performance</strong>. Rails has always been built on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shared_nothing_architecture">shared nothing architecture</a>, where in theory the only thing you need to do to scale out your app is to throw more hardware at it – the app should scale linearly. Of course there are limits to this, but they are by no means specific to Rails or Ruby.</p>

<p>Scaling and performance are two separate things. They are related as terms, but not strictly connected. Your app can be very fast for a couple users but awful for a thousand (didn&rsquo;t scale). Or it can scale at O(1) to a million users but loading a page for even a single concurrent user can take 10 seconds (scales but doesn&rsquo;t perform).</p>

<p>Like stated above, a traditional crud-style app on Rails can be made to scale very well by just adding app server instances, cores, and finally physical app servers serving the app. This is what is meant by scaling out<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Most often the limiting factor here is not Rails but the datastore, which is still often the one shared component in the equation. Scaling the database out is still harder than the appservers, but nevertheless possible. That is way outside the scope of this article, however.</p>

<h2>Is this the right tool for the job?</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s clear in hindsight that a Rails app wasn&rsquo;t the right tool for what Twitter became – a juggernaut where millions of people were basically realtime chatting with the whole world.</p>

<p>That doesn&rsquo;t mean that Rails wasn&rsquo;t a valid choice for the original app. Maybe it wasn&rsquo;t the best option even then from the technical perspective, but it for sure made developing Twitter a whole lot faster in its initial stages. You know, twitter wasn&rsquo;t the only contender in the microblogging stage in the late naughties. We finns fondly remember Jaiku. Then there was that other San Fransisco startup using Django that I can&rsquo;t even name anymore.</p>

<p>Anyway, the point is that <em>reaching a scale where you have to think harder about scalability is a very, very nice problem to have</em>. Either you built a real business and are making money hand over fist, or you are playing – and winning – the eyeball lotto and have VCs knocking on your door (or, more realistically, have taken on several millions already). The vast majority of businesses <em>never</em> reach this stage.</p>

<p>More likely you just fail in the hockeystick game (the VC option), or perhaps build a sustainable business (the old-fashioned <em>people pay me for helping them kick ass</em> kind). In any case, you won&rsquo;t have to worry about scaling to millions of concurrent users.</p>

<p>Even at the very profitable, high scale SaaS market there are hoards of examples of apps running on Rails. Kissmetrics runs its frontend on Rails, as does GitHub, not to mention Groupon, Livingsocial<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, and many others.</p>

<p>However, at certain scale you have to go for a more modular architecture, SOA if I may. You can use a message queue for message passing, a noSQL db for non-relational and ephemeral data, node.js for realtime apps, and so on. <em>A good tool for every particular sub-task of your app</em>.</p>

<p>That said, you need to keep in mind what I said above. It is pretty unlikely you will ever reach a state where you really need to scale. Thus, thinking about the architecture at the initial stage too much is a form of premature optimization. As long as you don&rsquo;t do anything extra stupid, you can probably get away with a simple Rails app. Because splitting up your app to lots of components early on makes several things harder and more expensive:</p>

<ul>
<li>Complexity of development.</li>
<li>Operating and deploying a bunch of different apps.</li>
<li>Keeping track that all apps are up and running.</li>
<li>Hunting bugs.</li>
<li>Making changes in a lean development environment where things change rapidly</li>
<li>Cognitive cost of understanding and learning how the app works. This is especially true when you&rsquo;re expanding your team.</li>
</ul>


<p>This doesn&rsquo;t mean that at some point you shouldn&rsquo;t do the split. There might be a time where the scale for the points above tips, and a monorail app becomes a burden. But then again, <em>there might not</em>. So do what makes sense now, not what makes sense in your imaginary future.</p>

<p>Of <em>course</em> Rails alone won&rsquo;t scale to a gazillion users for an app it wasn&rsquo;t really meant for to begin with. Neither is it supposed to. However, it is amazing how far you can get with it, just the same way that the old boring PostgreSQL still beats the shit out of its more &ldquo;modern&rdquo; competitors in most common usecases<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h2>Questions you should be asking</h2>

<p>When making a technology decision, instead of “Does is scale?”, here&rsquo;s what you should be asking instead:</p>

<ul>
<li>What is the right tool for the jobs of my app?</li>
<li>How far can I likely get away with a single Rails app?</li>
<li>Will we ever really reach the scale we claim in our investor prospectus? No need to lie to yourself here.</li>
<li>What is more important: getting the app up and running and in front of real users fast, or making it scalable in an imaginary future that may never come?</li>
</ul>


<p>Only after answering those are you equipped to make a decision.</p>

<p>P.S. Reached the point where optimizing Rails and Ruby performance <em>does</em> make a difference? We&rsquo;re writing <a href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/categories/rails-performance/">a series of articles</a> about just that. Pop your details in the <a href="#mc_embed_signup">form ☟ down there</a> and we&rsquo;ll keep you posted.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Another good one I heard in EuroOSCON 2005 was that the only thing good about Rails is its marketing.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Versus scaling up, which means making the single core or thread faster.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>OK, the last two might not pass the profitable bit.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>There are obviously special cases where a single Rails app doesn&rsquo;t cut it even from the beginning. E.g. computationally intensive apps such as Kissmetrics or Skylight.io obviously won&rsquo;t run their stats aggregation processes on Rails.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Garbage Collection: Naive Defaults]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/rails-garbage-collection-naive-defaults/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-04T17:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/rails-garbage-collection-naive-defaults</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/x1klima/13349077375/in/photolist-mkBvCt-9F5bop-psoHyh-6pkzNo-9uDMLx-85EMnZ-ibSsrK-iog9vf-JtxCJ-iohdxP-ibS242-7RtfVT-k1H87W-jNAG6M-oxaFaw-cR3ow7-gEqUsd-6z6KY5-e1m1pQ-diRWXG-i5md69-iogg32-ibSVHi-ibStrn-ibSVUy-n8CpB1-67QKGw-p3qtEX-4THpny-ebLNCE-nycgpC-6U69md-4yXv5b-pTDf3R-861fmQ-6zABJu-3FKVM-nwzafz-6pgrY2-9ejbm6-QuSM-hvn32M-aomUMi-9eebae-b15Lpi-8tBhZj-6o1Xmn-6z3YKz-5s868-61WvU1"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7036/13349077375_36fc92ecce_k_d.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><small>Photo by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/x1klima/13349077375/in/photolist-mkBvCt-9F5bop-psoHyh-6pkzNo-9uDMLx-85EMnZ-ibSsrK-iog9vf-JtxCJ-iohdxP-ibS242-7RtfVT-k1H87W-jNAG6M-oxaFaw-cR3ow7-gEqUsd-6z6KY5-e1m1pQ-diRWXG-i5md69-iogg32-ibSVHi-ibStrn-ibSVUy-n8CpB1-67QKGw-p3qtEX-4THpny-ebLNCE-nycgpC-6U69md-4yXv5b-pTDf3R-861fmQ-6zABJu-3FKVM-nwzafz-6pgrY2-9ejbm6-QuSM-hvn32M-aomUMi-9eebae-b15Lpi-8tBhZj-6o1Xmn-6z3YKz-5s868-61WvU1">martin</a>, used under the Creative Commons license.</small></p>

<p>The vast majority of <a href="http://www.rubyonrails.org">Ruby on Rails</a> applications deploy to production with the vanilla Ruby GC configuration. A conservative combination of growth factors and accounting that &ldquo;works&rdquo; for a demographic from IRB sessions (still my preferred calculator) to massive monolithic Rails apps (the fate of most successful ones). In practice this doesn&rsquo;t work very well, however. It produces:</p>

<ul>
<li>Too aggressive growth of Ruby heap slots and pages when thresholds are reached.</li>
<li>A large ratio of short and medium lived objects in relation to long lived ones for Rails applications.</li>
<li>Too many intermittent major GC cycles during the request / response cycle.</li>
<li>Heap fragmentation.</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s use a metaphor most of us can better relate to: <em>dreaded household chores.</em> Your ability and frequency of hosting dinners at home are limited by four things (takeaways and paper plates aside):</p>

<ul>
<li>How many seats and tables you have</li>
<li>How many sets of clean cutlery, plates and glasses are available</li>
<li>Overhead preparing a particular choice of cuisine</li>
<li>Willingness to clean up and do dishes after</li>
</ul>


<p>This is what you have to work with at home:</p>

<ul>
<li>4 chairs and a table</li>
<li>12 plates and equivalent utensils</li>
<li>83 friends (60 from Facebook, 20 at work, your 2 brothers and then there&rsquo;s Jim)</li>
<li>3 wine glasses and a beer mug</li>
<li>1 bottle of wine and 24 beers<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
<li>3 awesome steaks and a piece of tofu</li>
<li>Fresh local produce</li>
</ul>


<p>Some of your friends are also vegetarian.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s have a look at two different scenarios.</p>

<h4>IRB scenario</h4>

<p>You&rsquo;ve invited and subsequently prepared dinner and the table—seats, plates and cutlery sets—for four, popped open your bottle of wine and fired up the grill. However, only one friend arrives, quite late. You&rsquo;re grilling steak number three, yet he&rsquo;s the vegetarian…and only drinks beer. And even then doesn&rsquo;t talk very much.</p>

<p>In the end, you down the whole bottle of wine and the three steaks. Life&rsquo;s good again. There&rsquo;s plenty to clean up and pack away, still.</p>

<h4>Rails scenario</h4>

<p>17 guests show up at your door. Half of them are heavily intoxicated because Dylan invited the rest of his wine tasting group, too. Only one eats any of your food, yet breaks four plates. Beer disappeared in three minutes. The group members reveal seven new bottles of wine, make your dog drink one and he kernel panics as a result.</p>

<p>You were not f*cking prepared. At all. Marinated steak&rsquo;s now ruined, there&rsquo;s less inventory and 30+ bottles to recycle. You&rsquo;re hungry and now there are no plates left!</p>

<p>In both of these scenarios, from the perspective of your friends it mostly worked out just fine. It wasn&rsquo;t optimal for you or your environment, though. What&rsquo;s important is that you learned a few things:</p>

<ul>
<li>Next time it&rsquo;s easier to execute optimally, but there may still be a party and some broken plates.</li>
<li>A barbeque for 17 in your one bedroom flat with a George Foreman grill doesn&rsquo;t scale well.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cooking with Ruby</h2>

<p>In the same manner, different use cases for the Ruby runtime require different preparations. Let&rsquo;s tie the dinner metaphor back to Ruby land and its memory model.</p>

<h4>Home environment</h4>

<p>The Ruby runtime, with everything else inside. Pages, objects and auxilary object data.</p>

<h4>Guest count</h4>

<p>The number of major features and facets you need to support. Gems and engines are good candidates along with individual models, controllers, views etc. These &ldquo;seats&rdquo; are also connected - different guests mingle together.</p>

<h4>Guest distribution</h4>

<p>Rails provides a framework for building applications, thus should be considered as part of the guest list too. Like some family members that make their way to gettogethers. First and second tier cousins you may hear of once a year and never talk with - they&rsquo;re present (consume memory), yet don&rsquo;t always add much value to the ambient.</p>

<h4>Food and drink</h4>

<p>The amount and distribution of objects required to make a feature or facet work. A mix bag of small entrees (embedded objects like 2-char strings), main dishes (a Rails request and all its context) to cocktails and tequila shots (threads!).</p>

<h4>Plates and glasses</h4>

<p>An object slot on the Ruby heap. One String, Array, Hash or any other object. Keep in mind that they can overflow and be recycled too - a wine glass is good for multiple servings. For buffets, a single plate can go very far too :-)</p>

<h4>Tables</h4>

<p>Ruby pages - containers for objects. All of the plates and glasses on a given table. They&rsquo;re mostly prepared in advance, but you can &ldquo;construct&rdquo; and improvise as needed to.</p>

<h4>Type of cuisine</h4>

<p>Some dishes incur a lot of work to prepare <em>and</em> to clean up. Cooked basmati rice will leave a very very different footprint in your kitchen than a paella or salmon option would.</p>

<p>The GC defaults for most Rails applications assume a reasonable sized home environment, a well defined guest list and just enough food and drinks for each. Everyone can sit at the same table, wine and dine on fine dishes, all with a minimal cleanup burden.</p>

<p><em>In reality, it&rsquo;s a frat party. Gone seriously wrong.</em></p>

<p><em>In the next part of this series, we&rsquo;re going to take a look at how the Ruby runtime can better host Rails applications. And what you can optimize for.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Because if there&rsquo;s a promotion, you buy.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
