<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Philosophy | Bear Metal]]></title>
  <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/categories/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-12T13:32:39+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://bearmetal.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bear Metal OÜ]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Not About You]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-you/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-12T13:32:39+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a slightly expanded version of a talk I gave in <a href="http://railsgirls.com/helsinki">Rails Girls Helsinki</a> in February 2015.</em></p>

<p><figure markdown="1">
  <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/11984559914/">
    <img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3728/11984559914_be77fb9031_o_d.png">
  </a></p>

<p>  <figcaption>
    <p>
      Photo by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/smemon/11984559914/">Sean MacEntee</a>, used under a Creative Commons license.
    </p>
  </figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>I used to suffer from terrible stage fright. I was super nervous every time I presented. I forgot stuff I was supposed to say on stage. I never vomited before a talk, though, I’ll give you that.</p>

<p>It got better over time through lots of practice, but I still get all sweaty and shaky before getting on stage.</p>

<p>Then I recently stumbled upon an article by Kathy Sierra called <a href="http://seriouspony.com/blog/2013/10/4/presentation-skills-considered-harmful">Presentation Skills Considered Harmful</a>. In it she tells about having had similar problems, and how all the tutorials told her what and how you should do to give a good presentation. You, you, you.</p>

<p>Then she realized that a presentation is really a UX. <em>A presentation is just a user experience</em>. You present ideas – hopefully good ones – to your audience. What does this make you, the presenter? A UI. You are just a UI, a user interface. <em>You</em> yourself don’t matter that much. All that matters is that your ideas touch your audience.</p>

<p>Is that bad? No, it’s great. It’s a huge relief. What matters is  not you but what you have to say, the meat of your talk.</p>

<p>And that brings us nicely to the topic of this article.</p>

<p><strong>It’s not about you.</strong></p>

<p>This is maybe the most important thing I’ve learned during the past decade<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. It’s also not only profound, but spans your entire life.</p>

<h2>Writing</h2>

<p>These days, everyone and their cat has a blog.</p>

<p>Most blogs tell about the author, which is totally fine — if the author writes it for themselves or their relatives. But when you think about the most helpful blogs – the ones you go back to all the time – they really aren’t. They are about helping the reader, either by informing them or teaching them new things.</p>

<p><em>But Jarkko</em>, I hear you say. <em>You just started this article with a story about yourself</em>.</p>

<p>That is correct. Storytelling gets kind of an exception.</p>

<p>Except not really. Because storytelling isn’t really about the storyteller, either. You know, we didn’t always know how to write. Telling stories was the only way to pass information to younger generations. Thus, our brains are quite literally wired to react to storytelling. <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5965703/the-science-of-storytelling-why-telling-a-story-is-the-most-powerful-way-to-activate-our-brains">We’re evolutionarily built to learn better from stories</a>.</p>

<p>Thus, stories are not so much about you, the teller, either. Stories are about the listener/reader, and how they relate to the protagonist of the narrative.</p>

<p>And in the end, unless you’re writing fiction, stories are just a tool as well. A powerful one, yes, but just a tool to bring home a lesson to the reader.</p>

<p><em>Because writing is not about you.</em></p>

<p>Cincinnati Enquirer learned this the hard way recently. After they laid off their whole copy desk, they were <em>shocked</em> to find out that readers were outraged about the deteriorating quality of the paper’s articles. John E. McIntyre <a href="http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/language-blog/bal-first-lesson-nobody-cares-20150211-story.html">describes the issue</a> vividly:</p>

<blockquote><p>The reader doesn’t care how hard you worked, what pressures you are under, or how good your intentions are. The reader sees the product, online or in print; if the product looks sloppy and substandard, the reader will form, and likely express, a low opinion of it. And the reader is under no obligation whatsoever to be kind.</p></blockquote>

<p>What the Enquirer forgot was that <em>their writing is really not about them</em>.</p>

<p>But you don’t wanna hear me babble about writing, let’s get to business.</p>

<h2>Business ideas</h2>

<p>Are you still looking for that killer business idea?</p>

<p>Stop.</p>

<p>Ideas are all about you. How to get into business <em>you</em> should – apparently through divine intervention or something – come up with a dazzling idea.</p>

<p><a href="https://unicornfree.com/2013/how-do-you-create-a-product-people-want-to-buy">Ideas are also dangerous</a> because once you get one, it makes you a victim of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias">confirmation bias</a>. You’re going to start retrofitting the world to your idea, which is totally backwards.</p>

<p>Instead, find an audience you can relate to and sell to. Then, find about their pains, problems, and ways to help them make more money. Then solve that pain and you’ll do well.</p>

<p>Because – to quote Peter Drucker – the purpose of business is to create and keep a customer. It’s that customer, not you, who is going to decide the fate of your business.</p>

<p><em>Because successful business isn’t about you.</em></p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>You know what’s special about Apple ads? They almost never list features or specs. Instead, they show what their users can do with them. Shoot video. <em>Facetime</em> with their relatives on the other side of globe. Throw a DJ gig with just an iPad or two.</p>

<p>My friend Amy Hoy has this formula for great sales copy called <a href="https://unicornfree.com/2013/how-i-increased-conversion-2-4x-with-better-copywriting">PDF, for Pain–Dream–Fix</a>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with describing the pain your users are having, with crisp, clear words, so that they will go all <em>ahhh, they understand me</em>.</li>
<li>Then flip it around.
 <em>“Imagine a world where you wouldn’t have to manually scan your taxi receipts. Instead, they would magically appear in your accounting system.”</em></li>
<li>And fix.
 <em>“We got you covered. Uberreceipt 9000 will hook up Uber with your accounting and you will never again touch another taxi receipt!”</em></li>
</ol>


<p>Now <em>that</em> is how you make people pay attention.</p>

<p>Because <em>great marketing and sales copy is not about you</em>, either.</p>

<h2>Finally: Product</h2>

<p>Last, and indeed least, we get to the actual product, software in our case.</p>

<p><em>It – as and of itself – is not all that important</em>. Because having a great product is not about you, or the product itself. It’s about solving a customer pain or a job they need to tackle.</p>

<p>Because people don’t buy a quarter-inch drill, they buy a quarter-inch hole in the wall.</p>

<p>By now, you already know the pains of your audience<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Now it’s time to solve them. From previous points, you should already have a nice roadmap to a product people like.</p>

<h2>Extra credit: Make your users kick ass</h2>

<p>For an extra credit, let’s see how we could transform people from liking your product to loving and raving about it.</p>

<p>We started this talk with Kathy Sierra, and we’re going to end it with her as well.</p>

<p>Kathy’s <a href="http://businessofsoftware.org/2013/02/kathy-sierra-building-the-minimum-badass-user-business-of-software-a-masterclass-in-thinking-about-software-product-development/">big idea</a> is that the main purpose of software is to make its users kick ass. What she means by this is that software – or any product really – should help their users to get better at what they do, not just using the product<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p><em>Screw gamification.</em></p>

<p>Final Cut Pro should not make its users better at using Final Cut Pro. <em>It should make them better film editors.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.wodconnect.com">WODConnect</a> should not make its users better at using the app. <em>It should make them stronger and faster.</em></p>

<p>This should happen through <em>everything</em> related to your product. The product itself, its marketing, its manuals, its customer support, everything.</p>

<p>Because your success is not about you or your product.</p>

<p>It’s about the users.</p>

<p>It’s about empathy.</p>

<hr />

<p>Discuss on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9038804">Hacker News</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Well, let’s just say it’s a tie with learning about the <a href="http://mindsetonline.com">growth mindset</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>If not, go back to the Business Ideas part above. Do not  – and I can’t stress this enough – start building a product before you are sure it solves a problem people have, know they have, and are willing to pay for.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>All this is also the subject of Kathy’s upcoming book, <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920036593.do">Badass: Making Users Awesome</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Of Course You May Eat Your Own Food Here]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/of-course-you-may-eat-your-own-food-here/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T16:00:18+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/of-course-you-may-eat-your-own-food-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you with or against your customers?</p>

<p>Do your signs read like those “Private property. Keep out!” signs? “No eating of own food”. “Food may not be taken out of the restaurant!” Don&rsquo;t you have more important things to care about, like, whether your customers love you?</p>

<p>I recently saw this sign on the outside wall of a small roadside restaurant<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/IMG_2928.JPG" alt="" /></p>

<p>It reads: “You may of course eat your own food here as well.”</p>

<p>So, why should you be more like Tiinan Tupa and less like ABC?</p>

<p>First of all, very few people will probably abuse it. Even if someone eats their own lunch packs there, they will probably reciprocate and buy something as a favor to the place.</p>

<p>Second, it is the ultimate <a href="http://www.sethgodin.com/purple/">purple cow</a>. It is something unexpected, something remarkable people will pay attention to. People are so accustomed to passive-aggressive notes forbidding this and that that a sign being actually nice will be noticed and talked about.</p>

<p>Lastly, and most importantly, it&rsquo;s just plain being nice. So stop just using glorious and empty words about how you care about your customers and actually walk the walk.</p>

<p>For these three reasons, being ridiculously admitting with your customers will probably also be good for you in the long term. So stop picking nickels in front of bulldozers. Make sure people will give you money <em>because they love you</em>, not because they <em>have to</em>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Coincidentally, I found it on Vaihtoehto ABC:lle, a site and an app dedicated to finding alternatives to the ubiquitous, generic and boring ABC gas station chain that seems to have infiltrated the whole country in just a couple of years. ABC specifically forbids eating food bought from its own supermarket in the cafeteria of the same gas station.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do You Know the Biggest Reason for Why Enterprise Software Sucks?]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/do-you-know-the-biggest-reason-why-enterprise-software-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T11:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/do-you-know-the-biggest-reason-why-enterprise-software-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>We all know the story. Your company was going to get this big new shiny ERP software. It was going to replace a third of the workforce in the company, cut the costs in half and make everyone happy. In reality the project went two years over schedule, cost three times as much as envisioned, and the end result was a steaming pile of shit.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/53326337@N00/8043877054/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8453/8043877054_883963cf80_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><small>Photo by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/53326337@N00/8043877054/">Quinn Dombrowski</a>, used under the Creative Commons license.</small></p>

<p>At this point started the blame-throwing. The provider duped the client with waterfall and exorbitant change fees. The buyer didn&rsquo;t know how to act as a client in an information system project. The specs weren&rsquo;t good/detailed/strict/loose enough. The consultants just weren&rsquo;t that good in the first place. On and on and on.</p>

<p>While one or more of the above invariably are true in failed software projects, there&rsquo;s one issue that almost each and every failed enterprise software project has in common: <em>the buyers were not (going to be) the users of the software</em>.</p>

<p>This simple fact has huge implications. Ever heard that “the client didn&rsquo;t really know what they wanted”? Well, that&rsquo;s because they didn&rsquo;t. Thus, most such software projects are built with something completely different than the end user in mind. Be it the ego of the CTO, his debt to his mason brothers who happen to be in the software business<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, or just the cheapest initial bid<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. In any case, it&rsquo;s in the software provider&rsquo;s best interest to appeal to the decisionmaker, not the people actually using the system.</p>

<p>Of course, not every software buyer is as bad as described above. Many truly care about the success of the system and even its users. If for no other reason, at least because it has a direct effect on the company&rsquo;s bottom line. But even then, they just don&rsquo;t have the first-hand experience of working in the daily churn. They simply can&rsquo;t know what&rsquo;s best for the users. Of course, this gets even worse in the design-by-committee, big-spec-upfront projects.</p>

<p>Since it&rsquo;s not very likely that we could change the process of making large software project purchases any time soon, what can we as software vendors do? One word: <em>empathy</em>. If you just take a spec and implement it with no questions asked, shame on you. You deserve all the blame. Your job is not to implement what the spec says. Heck, your job isn&rsquo;t even to create what the client wants. Your job is to build what the client – no, the end users – need. For this – no matter how blasphemous it might sound to an engineer – you have to actually <em>talk</em> to the people that will be using your software.</p>

<p>This is why it&rsquo;s so important to put the software developers to actually do what the end-users would. <strong>If you&rsquo;re building call-center software, make the developers work in the call center a day or a week. If you&rsquo;re building web apps, make the developers and designers work the support queue, don&rsquo;t just outsource it to India.</strong></p>

<p>There is no better way to understand the needs for software you&rsquo;re building than to talk directly to its users or use it yourself for real, in a real-life situation. While there aren&rsquo;t that many opportunities to dog-fooding when building (perhaps internal) enterprise software for a client, there&rsquo;s nothing preventing you from sending your people to the actual cost center. Nothing will give as much insight to the needs and pains of the actual users. No spec will ever give you as broad a picture. No technical brilliance will ever make up for lacking domain knowledge. And no client will ever love you as much as the one in the project where you threw yourself (even without being asked) on the line of fire. That&rsquo;s what we here at Bear Metal insist on doing at the start of every project. I think you should, too.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>We at Bear Metal have some availability open for short and mid-term projects. If you&rsquo;re looking for help building, running, scaling or marketing your web app,  <a href="mailto:info@bearmetal.eu">get in touch</a>.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>It&rsquo;s surprising how often the same people actually represent both the buyer and the seller. This happens all the time e.g. in the patient care systems projects.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Nevermind that the cheapest initial bid almost always balloons to something completely different in the end.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It’s Not About Us, It’s About You (and Not Really About You, Either)]]></title>
    <link href="https://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-us-its-about-you/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T15:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>https://bearmetal.eu/theden/its-not-about-us-its-about-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><figure markdown="1">
  <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/22711505@N05/8987537991/in/photolist-eGctVz-Rw9Az-RVB46-d1oXub-3od3r2-5maP4G-d1pEjS-2z4E45-7zg9zD-dk9TPx-dk9ViL-62gdUK-cbhisA-dk9VoE-6sjCDX-6sjCQ4-8EcAxc-d1pPAm-aSuUEX-7WR5Va-9SMEDS-mzFjV-9SrEU9-5bvnMg-bbvqpn-6S8uV4-6ScRvQ-8ypVzY-bbvqoz-7YzNHn-eecQ8W-d1pDv9-6QYGRg-62QwZR-fbZJU2-bXZ3iw-hZ9cW-hZ9cX-hZa5p-hZa5q-5iHQyg-4SnuGn-g5GYQ-9dbkFa-b5vRQc-d1pF7C-5oG5br-bcHysn-c3QYZW-c3QYiN-749XSZ/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2859/8987537991_795f7568ca_h.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>  <figcaption markdown="1">
    <p>Photo by <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/22711505@N05/8987537991/in/photolist-eGctVz-Rw9Az-RVB46-d1oXub-3od3r2-5maP4G-d1pEjS-2z4E45-7zg9zD-dk9TPx-dk9ViL-62gdUK-cbhisA-dk9VoE-6sjCDX-6sjCQ4-8EcAxc-d1pPAm-aSuUEX-7WR5Va-9SMEDS-mzFjV-9SrEU9-5bvnMg-bbvqpn-6S8uV4-6ScRvQ-8ypVzY-bbvqoz-7YzNHn-eecQ8W-d1pDv9-6QYGRg-62QwZR-fbZJU2-bXZ3iw-hZ9cW-hZ9cX-hZa5p-hZa5q-5iHQyg-4SnuGn-g5GYQ-9dbkFa-b5vRQc-d1pF7C-5oG5br-bcHysn-c3QYZW-c3QYiN-749XSZ/">Ron Cogswell</a></p>
  </figcaption>
</figure></p>

<p>One of the saddest things to happen online was in 2007 when my all-time favorite author and presenter, Kathy Sierra, received death threaths and thus retreated from the public web. It also meant that she stopped writing her <a href="http://headrush.typepad.com">Creating Passionate Users</a> weblog, which had been a great inspiration for me for quite some time. Thank god she didn&rsquo;t <a href="http://ejohn.org/blog/eulogy-to-_why/">pull a _why</a> on it.</p>

<p>While it’s more than six years since Kathy’s last blog post (is it really that long?), there is no reason we shouldn’t apply her lessons even in today&rsquo;s online world.</p>

<p>Maybe the most famous mantra of Sierra was that in order to create passionate users you should make <em>them</em> kick ass. Sure, it’s nice if your UI boasts übercool 3D CSS transformations but if it doesn’t help your users shine, no one (well, except for some web geeks) will give a flying fuck.</p>

<p>She demonstrated this with the fact that very often companies spend a huge amount of effort and money to hone the living daylights off their marketing materials but don&rsquo;t really put that much time into what actually helps their users: tutorials and user manuals. Of course this had helped her immensively by creating a market for the visual <a href="http://www.headfirstlabs.com">Head First</a> book series on O&#8217;Reilly that she curated.</p>

<p>Apple has for a long time been a good example of helping its users kick ass. The user manual of the old Final Cut Pro 7 was also a great introduction to the art of video editing<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Likewise, most of Apple ads show things you can do and <em>create</em> with their products, not just random people dancing around the pool.</p>

<p>People care about how they can kick ass <em>themselves</em> and they need to be able to learn it to capitalize on it. Nowadays it seems that companies are much more interested in giving people free apps and then using psychological tricks to milk money out of them than helping them shine. Which, coincidentally, brings us back to Kathy Sierra.</p>

<p>To my pleasant surprise, I last week learned that Kathy is back with the pseudonym <a href="https://twitter.com/seriouspony">Serious Pony</a>, and <a href="http://seriouspony.com/blog/">a new blog</a> of the same name. The first article, <a href="http://seriouspony.com/blog/2013/7/24/your-app-makes-me-fat">Your app makes me fat</a>, is of the same awesome quality as her old pieces. In it, she tackles head-on the aforementioned gamification trend and the <a href="http://youarenotsosmart.com/2012/04/17/ego-depletion/">ego depletion</a> tax it puts on us as app users.</p>

<p>To honor Kathy, we wanted to start this blog off by not talking about us ourselves, because <a href="http://youarenotsosmart.com/2012/04/17/ego-depletion/">Bear Metal</a> isn&rsquo;t really about us, but you. And – assuming you are a developer, entrepreneur or content provider – not really about you either. It&rsquo;s about who we (you and us) serve. Because without them there is no market, no audience, no need, no problems to solve, no pains to relieve. Your customers should be the ones that matter to you. And they don&rsquo;t care about you or us. They care about whether your product can make them shine.</p>

<p>Can your product help <em>them kick ass</em>? <em>Does it</em>? Are you <em>communicating that effectively</em> to your current and potential customers? That is all that should matter.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unfortunately this can&rsquo;t be said about the manual of the new version, Final Cut Pro X.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
